<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xm-well_formed path="F:\Special Collections\EADXML\web text\webtext2006\generalinfo2006.dtd"?>
<div> <h1>General Information</h1> <ol> <li> <a href="#intro">Introduction</a>
</li> <li> <a href="#hist">Project History</a> </li> <li> <a
href="#access">Participating Institutions</a> </li> <li> <a
href="#tech">Technical Information</a> </li> </ol> <h2> <a
name="intro">Introduction</a> </h2> <p>The Irish Literary Collections Portal
provides access to the finding aids of over 100 of North America's Irish
literary manuscript collections. The collections represented in the portal
range in date from the Irish Literary Renaissance to the present and contain a
wide variety of materials including correspondence, manuscripts and typescripts
of literary works, photographs, and printed material. Researchers should note
that this site contains descriptions of collections rather than electronic
versions of the individual items within these collections.</p> <p>Finding aids
are tools created by archivists to present detailed information about the
content and organization of a collection. This information enables researchers
to browse a collection and to locate specific materials of interest. Though
finding aids vary in length and level of detail, they generally consist of the
following: a biographical or historical sketch, a scope and content note, an
outline of the collection’s organization or series arrangement, relevant
administrative information about copyright and restrictions, and a detailed
container list of numbered boxes and folders along with a description of their
contents. </p> <p>This portal brings together finding aids from a number of
institutions into a single searchable database. The "Search" function allows
researchers to conduct keyword searches within the finding aids and to filter
those searches by creator and/or repository. By using the "Browse" function,
researchers may quickly view an alphabetical listing of all the collections
available through the portal. Entire finding aids may be downloaded and printed
in PDF-format.</p> <h2> <a name="hist">Project History</a></h2> <p>In 2001, a
two-year grant from the <a HREF="http://www.delmas.org/">The Gladys Krieble
Delmas Foundation</a> helped Emory University and Boston College to digitize
finding aids and develop a search interface that allows scholars both on- and
off-site to explore the collections and quickly find relevant materials. In
2006, a second grant from the Delmas Foundation allowed the project to
incorporate the finding aids of Irish literary manuscript collections at
several additional repositories.</p><h2> <a name="access">Participating
institutions</a></h2> <p>General information on the hours, location, and access
to the collections contained in the Irish Literary Collections Portal may be
found at the following web sites: </p> <h3><a
href="http://www.bc.edu/libraries/centers/burns/">Boston College, John J. Burns
Library, Archives and Manuscripts</a></h3><h3><a
href="http://specialcollections.library.emory.edu/">Emory University,
Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library</a></h3><h3><a
href="http://www.libraries.psu.edu/speccolls/rbm/">Pennsylvania State
University, Special Collections Library, Rare Books and
Manuscripts</a></h3><h3><a
href="http://www.lib.siu.edu/departments/speccoll">Southern Illinois University
Carbondale, Morris Library, Special Collections Research Center</a></h3><h3><a
href="http://www.lib.udel.edu/ud/spec/">University of Delaware Library, Special
Collections</a></h3><h3><a href="http://www.hrc.utexas.edu/">University of
Texas at Austin, Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center</a></h3><h3><a
href="http://zsr.wfu.edu/collections/special/">Wake Forest University, Z. Smith
Reynolds Library</a></h3><h3><a
href="http://library.wustl.edu/units/spec/">Washington University at St. Louis,
Department of Special Collections</a></h3><h2> <a name="tech">Technical
Information</a> </h2> <p>The findings aids for this project have been encoded
using the <a href="http://www.loc.gov/ead/">Encoded Archival Description</a>
document type definition (EAD.DTD), Version 2002, an XML-compliant data
structure developed and maintained jointly by the Society of American
Archivists and the Library of Congress. </p> <p>Three EAD templates based on
the complexity of the finding aid were created in X-Metal: a non-series
template, a series template, and a subseries template. Using the
<a href="http://www.rlg.org/rlgead/eadguides.html">RLG Best Practice Guidelines
for Encoded Archival Description</a> (RLG EAD Advisory Group, August 2002), we
incorporated recommended ID attributes, encoding analogs and the normalization
of dates in each EAD document. </p> <p>The finding aids were created in
Microsoft Word and the high-level elements were cut and pasted into the
appropriate X-Metal template. Each component-level container list was converted
to a text file and then run through a perl script which applied the appropriate
tagging. The container lists were then cut and pasted back into the template in
X-Metal.</p> <p>Further transformations of the X-Metal data were made through a
process written in <a href="http://ant.apache.org/">Apache Ant</a>: replacing
bad data (invalid utf-8 characters introduced by Microsoft Word), changing
entities to unicode, adding a unique id for most elements, and creating
<a href="http://exist.sourceforge.net/">eXist</a> database load files.</p>
<p>The data was loaded into a eXist database and was then retrieved with Tamino
X-Query calls. X-Query implements a subset of the
<a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xpath">XPath</a> specification (a W3C
recommendation). Web pages were dynamically generated with
<a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt">XSL</a> Transformations (a W3C
recommendation) using the <a href="http://cocoon.apache.org/">Apache Cocoon</a>
XML publishing framework. Cocoon is run as a java servlet within the
<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/">Apache Tomcat</a> servlet engine.
</p></div>
